<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-12-01T04:17:47+00:00</updated><id>https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nitin Rai</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The script that helped me win 3MT thesis competition</title><link href="https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/blog/2023/3MT-Thesis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The script that helped me win 3MT thesis competition"/><published>2023-02-16T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-16T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/blog/2023/3MT-Thesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/blog/2023/3MT-Thesis/"><![CDATA[<p>After much considerations, I finally plan on writing a small post about the script (summary of my research) that helped me win NDSU’s annual 3MT Thesis competition. This was my first time (since the time I joined NDSU in the fall 2019) participating in the competition with 2-levels of rounds, preliminary and championship. Below is the script that I wrote and memorized it really hard while trying to speak atleat 5-times a day so that I don’t forget it when facing a large audience. My presentation was titled, <strong>Drone spots illegal weed plants: The future of agriculture takes flight</strong>. I have provided some strike-throughs (<del>this</del>, with changes made in the brackets) throughout the script that basically portrays how I navigated my script for the final talk after gathering advise from a mentor. Also, the bold fonts (<strong>This one</strong>) mean that an expression or an emphasis was required. 👨‍🔬</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/NR/assets/img/3MT_Nitin-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/NR/assets/img/3MT_Nitin-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/NR/assets/img/3MT_Nitin-1400.webp"/> <img src="/NR/assets/img/3MT_Nitin.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Dr. Colleen Fitzgerald, Vice President for Research and Creative Activity at North Dakota State University, handing over the prize money to me right after the competition. </div> <p><em>The script starts below…</em></p> <p>Have you ever <strong>wondered</strong> if an uncrewed aircraft system (UAS) or drones could be used to monitor agricultural farms? Well, I carried the <strong>same curiosity</strong> almost 3-and-a-half years back and now my research focuses on the application of drones in agriculture.</p> <p><em>My name is Nitin Rai and I am a Ph.D. candidate in the department of Agricultural and Biosystems Engineering.</em></p> <p>According to a survey, the world population is about to reach <strong>9 billion mark</strong> by the end of 2030. With this population growth rate, growers and farmers <strong>are expected to</strong> increase the use of technolgies that are reliable, fast, and sustainable. One such technologies are drones in agriculture that can be used to monitor weed growth. Now as we all know that weeds are unwanted plants that compete with crop plants for sunlight, water, and nutrients <del>thereby affecting its yield</del> (and what not). For example, a weed by the name of kochia was found to decrease corn production by over 90%. <del>These weeds could be identified by in-field machines and eradicated on-the-go.</del> (<strong>But there’s a hope!</strong>). Do you know that these weeds could be eliminated by such advanced technologies in real-time?</p> <p>Well allow me to do some time-travelling here <del>by taking you half a century back</del>. In the late 1970s, farmers had to <del>literally</del> walk miles in order to manually <del>apply herbicide solutions</del> (eliminate weeds). <del>Fast forwarded to</del> Another 20 years <del>and engineers developed conventional sprayers</del> (and we have big conventional sprayers). Fast-forwarded to another 20 years and we have drone technology. <strong>So, as a 21st century agricultural engineer, what role do I play in making advancements and contributions to such technologies?</strong> Well, the answer to this is: I teach drones to identify weeds <del>and that’s where I believe the future of agriculture is headed.</del> (amongst crop plants).</p> <p>So, questioning the gist of my research; how do I teach drones? <del>to spot weeds amongst crop plants?</del> Imagine teaching a 4 year old kid about how an apple looks like? Well you may <del>High chances are that you’re going to</del> start by describing its textures, such as, an apple is red color, it has a crisp texture, or is roundish in shape. <del>You may also show an image of an apple with different backgrounds and the next time the kid is with you in Walmart, he’ll certainly point out those red apples for a bite!</del> <strong>A computer is just like that 4 year old kid</strong>. In our research we collect <strong>thousands of images of weeds</strong> and <del>train</del> feed it <del>using an approach</del> in an algorithm called as machine learning algorithm. What these machine learning algorithms are capable of <del>doing</del> achieving is extracting <del>very specific features pertaining to</del> relevant features from a specific class of weed specie. <del>We then take these modeled algorithms and deploy them in multiple unseen locations.</del> Once we have these features modeled, we then take these models to multiple field locations to identify those weed species. <del>Once the algorithm identifies the weeds, we compare it with the ground truth data which are labeled by human experts.</del></p> <p>As far as the results <del>from our research is concerned</del> are concerned, our <del>trained</del> algorithm/model has been able to achieve an <strong>overall accuracy of over 85% in identifying 5 different species of weeds across 2 location in the state of ND</strong>. <del>With this accuracy</del> Moreover, our algorithm/model can be integrated with the technologies that are used by growers and farmers <del>would be able to integrate this technology with their spraying</del> to identify and spray weeds in their field as well. technology. <del>Moreover, our algorithm could be trained on small computers in less hours.</del></p> <p>So, does the future of agriculture takes flight <del>by monitoring your agricultural field</del>? <strong>Yes, of course it does!</strong> Therefore, the next time when you are about to eat a delicious meal, <strong>think about these technologies and farmers effort</strong> in quenching your starving tummy.</p> <p>Thank you!!! 😃</p> <p>P.S: If you’re interested in watching a recorded presentation, please click <a href="https://youtu.be/j3DfPBQiBS4">here</a>🥇.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="bib"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After much considerations, I finally plan on writing a small post about the script (summary of my research) that helped me win NDSU’s annual 3MT Thesis competition. This was my first time (since the time I joined NDSU in the fall 2019) participating in the competition with 2-levels of rounds, preliminary and championship. Below is the script that I wrote and memorized it really hard while trying to speak atleat 5-times a day so that I don’t forget it when facing a large audience. My presentation was titled, Drone spots illegal weed plants: The future of agriculture takes flight. I have provided some strike-throughs (this, with changes made in the brackets) throughout the script that basically portrays how I navigated my script for the final talk after gathering advise from a mentor. Also, the bold fonts (This one) mean that an expression or an emphasis was required. 👨‍🔬]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tennis Why do I love this sport</title><link href="https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/blog/2022/Tennis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tennis Why do I love this sport"/><published>2022-12-31T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-31T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/blog/2022/Tennis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/blog/2022/Tennis/"><![CDATA[<p>When I was 12 or 13, I vividly remember asking my dad if he could look for some tennis courts in the city (I did not own an Android phone back then!) and talk with the authorities to get me registered for playing tennis. The city that I was raised in India had only limited number of tennis courts owned by some big Clubs that charged high annual membership fees to allow its members to play tennis. With tennis in my heart, I grew up watching Federer and Nadal play and often used to think that hitting balls the way they did was easy. All you have to do is to be very energetic and active while you’re on the court. Alas! I WAS WRONG!!!</p> <blockquote> <p>There’s a yellow colored sticky note in my room that says, “Sports build character and that’s why Tennis”. Period.</p> </blockquote> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/NR/assets/img/tennis-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/NR/assets/img/tennis-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/NR/assets/img/tennis-1400.webp"/> <img src="/NR/assets/img/tennis.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Me trying a backhand while playing on one of the University Village Courts near NDSU-Main Campus. </div> <p>Years passed by and I never got a chance to play tennis until 2017. I got into IIT KGP to pursue my master’s study and it was for the first time when I saw 5–6 open tennis courts on-campus. My love for tennis was rejuvenated. But the biggest hurdle was to buy a good racquet and a set of balls to play with (which indeed was expensive!). I was a bit hesitant to ask my dad to sponsor a significant amount just to buy a racquet and set of balls (although I knew he would definitely pay for it!). However, I was able to talk with someone and managed to procure a Wilson racquet. Since then, I have been playing tennis and enjoying the sport more each day (but I am not consistent at all). Over time I have thought that I played many sports including, Volleyball, Cricket (I don’t like Cricket at all for some reason!), Squash, Badminton, Football (Soccer and not the American Football), Table-Tennis (Ping-pong), and Tennis (of-course). But I love tennis the most and is special to me due to following reasons:</p> <p><strong>Tennis demands mental strength:</strong> I won’t be bias at all if I say that tennis demands mental strength. That does not mean that the other sports does not. But playing tennis as singles is really exhausting and that too for 5-6 sets straight (think about the professionals!). It demands strong characters of an athelete. Tennis also involves strategic thinking ability to attack your opponent’ weakness + judging the balls. One has to be actively thinking and “BE PRESENT MENTALLY” on the court while playing this sport.</p> <p><strong>Tennis demands physical strength that leads to hitting strategic shots:</strong> This part is directly linked to the mental strength. If one can think to attack the opponent, one has to act too. In spite of not just simply running on the court, one should have charasmatic reflexes too in order to hit the ball just in the direction they might have thought. It requires a coordination between what one thinks and how one acts.  </p> <p><strong>Fighting for each point</strong>: In a way, tennis has taught me so much about life. No matter how challenging life can get on an every day basis (for points when playing), one always get an opportunity to fight back sometime! One of the major reason when I am on the court, I always have this inner feeling to fight and play the best as per my strength both mentally and physically.</p> <p><strong>Because of Rafael Nadal:</strong> The GOAT player of Tennis in my opinion. I wish I could see him play live someday soon. His amazing athleticism, control over his emotions for not breaking his tennis racquet (like Djoko and others), and not being disrespectful or abusive to this opponent. For me, this is a standalone quality of an amazing professional sports player.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="bib"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When I was 12 or 13, I vividly remember asking my dad if he could look for some tennis courts in the city (I did not own an Android phone back then!) and talk with the authorities to get me registered for playing tennis. The city that I was raised in India had only limited number of tennis courts owned by some big Clubs that charged high annual membership fees to allow its members to play tennis. With tennis in my heart, I grew up watching Federer and Nadal play and often used to think that hitting balls the way they did was easy. All you have to do is to be very energetic and active while you’re on the court. Alas! I WAS WRONG!!! There’s a yellow colored sticky note in my room that says, “Sports build character and that’s why Tennis”. Period.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nitin-dominic.github.io/NR/NR/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>